please watch your
breath e
come to the Garden
Room it's warm and the light
is
Rich and it covers all the objects in
the room like molten
gold e
enjoy the warmth of the room
look out the window at the sky blue
sky andless pleas
SK
e e
look at the mountains and the valley
that
separates your cabin from the
mountains the valley is covered with
light
also e
be content to stay looking at the valley
in the mountains
come back to the
room see your teacher seting in front of
you
and they're holding your hands in your
lap your hands are in
your your hands are in your hands and
your lap
it's just the focus on the touch of the
hand and there's nothing else in the
world
stay on the touch of the hand
do mind wanders catch it and and bring
it
back to the touch of the
hands e
come back to the touch of the hands
be happy and contented and to stay on
the touch of the
hand relax there take your rest
there just a touch of the
hand
e e
the Mind goes out the touch of the hands
catch it and bring it back e
come back to this
room slowly open your eyes
so we've
been talking about the fifth and sixth
stages of meditation okay
UHA and
sha uh doer you can you can translate as
controlling the
mind and Sh chip where you can translate
as quiet in the mind so five level five
out of the nine and level six out of the
nine at level five uh you
were overly concentrated within you were
uh coming inside too hard and then you
got Chao you got subtle
dullness which is characterized how do
you know when you have subtle
dullness uh you don't have any ignore
okay you don't have any intensity or you
still on the
object uh and the mind is rather fresh
but there's no excitement there's no uh
enjoyment of the object okay that would
be here okay he got uh subtle dullness
because he was focusing he was trying
too hard to bring the mind
in then at uh
shaa uh he had compensated
uh for the how do you say he had
compensated for the subtle dullness by
turning on S Tupa he he uplifted the
mind and then he went too far so he Jo
you know he corrected too far and then
he got subtle agitation okay which is
less common than
uh subtle donors
okay and both of these states
uh were achieved
through watchfulness shishin okay that's
what what's in his right hand he's
holding it
up and the two Critters are are getting
Almost White okay the two Critters are
are almost completely white by
now so we're on to number 23
we're on to number
23 this is another uh of the six Powers
okay we've reached another of the six
powers and this is the power of
effort
uh I was wondering why why they call it
the power of
[Music]
effort let's go through the power so far
and see okay so you got to you started
meditating because of the power of
hearing from your teacher in
instructions and then you used the Su
talk you thought about what your teacher
said then uh you used the
T which is uh the ability to pull back
the
object and then you got very good but at
this point where we are now you
finished you have a very powerful
ability to catch yourself going off the
object and then for some reason they say
uh what do you call it eort all right uh
I think it's as opposed to what comes
later right I think it's as opposed to
what comes there which is you can't say
right which is effortlessness okay so I
think they're emphasizing that this is
the last point at which you have to push
yourself a little bit and then after
that it's going on auto autoglide okay
so they call it
effort uh he says well let's go
back what the text says when you get to
number seven
which is up here 24 okay 23 was oh here
you're going to use the power of effort
okay and the text says here you use the
power of effort to achieve the seventh
and eighth levels of the nine levels use
the power of effort to achieve theate
love that's what uh section 23 says
then uh at 24 you've reached what we
call numbera which means completely
quieting the mind okay completely
quieting the
mind uh I'm going to read
the I I wrote a summary of the the text
on what's happening at
20 24 okay
okay this is from the larger text okay
at 24 your ability to bring the object
bring you bring your mind back to the
object and your watchfulness are DOA it
means they are completely mature and
Powerful
okay therefore CH means uh it's very
difficult at this point for you to get
any
dullness uh or to or to have your mind
go off to something you like okay
CH but you have to
use uh and this might help you define
what effort needs okay you have to use
the power of effort to prevent even
subtle forms of either one so uh subtle
dullness or subtle agitation
so at this point you're just dealing
with subtle dullness and subtle
agitation what is subtle dullness you
don't feel turned on by the object what
is subtle
agitation you feel like you might think
about lunching a few
seconds all right so at this point
uh if you want to know what he feels
effort refers to it's like the extra
going going the extra length that we say
in English going the extra length to
assure that you don't even have the
subtle forms of dullness and
agitation so that would be effort that
would be the meaning of effort effort
would be you're not satisfied to have a
pretty good meditation where you're
still on the object and your mind is
still fresh you want more you want
intensity okay and then and then you and
then effort is what takes you up to that
and then you don't want even those
subconscious about to happen thoughts
about lunch okay you don't even want uh
you can feel thoughts running under your
mind right you when you're in meditation
you can feel potential thoughts about
lunch running under their conscious mind
and they they you feel like they might
pop out okay so what he calls effort and
what he means by the word effort when he
says the power of effort is the slight
extra effort or the
extra I don't know attention you need to
stop even those two subtle forms of of
distraction so subtle dullness not
feeling turned on subtle
agitation uh tiny thoughts running under
your th and at this point you make the
extra effort to stop even
those this is distinguished from the
previous two by any great concern that
you will fall into subtle forms of Eed
so this is a very delicate there there's
a lot of argument and there's a lot of
discussion in the text about what's the
difference between 7 and 8 what's the
difference between 6 and 7 and the way
they phrase it in the ancient text at
this point is you have no great concern
that you will fall into subtle forms of
uh dullness or agitation that's a my
right okay so that the word great is the
is the key okay there's no serious
danger that you will fall into but that
implies that there is some danger okay
all right so the the way they
distinguish seven is they say no no
great danger or no serious danger that
you are going to
[Music]
fall and and then later in the same text
the author says there's no fear of great
active attacks from them so you there's
a metaphor which if we have time I'll go
through it but he
Compares uh the negative parts of your
mind to a boxing match okay and by this
time you're in the final
round okay and nobody's really taking
the offensive on anybody both guys are
just trying to stay up you know so you
know it's not like anyone's mounting a
major
offense uh both guys are just kind of
weaving and you know they're both ready
to fall down and no one can mount a
serious attack on the Earth
your even your subtle forms of dullness
and agitation at this point are unable
to mount a serious attack on your M but
they are still you know punching on a
while okay all right uh if we have time
I'll read you the whole metaphor it's
very beautiful because in the early
stages what in the first few rounds yeah
they're in control you know you're like
getting beat you're you're getting beat
you're in the corner and they're just
like like
okay all
right at this level it you just make a
slight effort and you can
block you can block what do you say in
tibetan they say shwa shwa means to Lose
Yourself uh jar Shore means to slip on
Ice you see uh like that so or Shore can
mean to lose a
game uh so here shwa means you're not
gonna
slip into you're not going to fall down
into you're not going to uncontrollably
fall down into agitation or dness but
you might like trip into there okay so
short means where you you know feet up
head down and you you land on your butt
you're not going to do that you're not
going to have a short ring but you might
have a small you know you might uh what
do you call slip without falling catch
yourself I get that's a good metaphor
cuz you at this point you're really good
at when you start to slip you can catch
yourself really fast and you won't get
any form of uh dullness or agitation
where you just totally fall into them
uncontrollably you like start and you
slip and you bring yourself back
okay uh we haven't had a state of mind
for a while if you noticed I'm sure you
were
concerned uh
we had a at the first two of the nine
levels we had a mode or a feeling you
could call it a feeling in the
meditation that you had to work really
hard to get into it okay Jim you had to
focus really hard to get into that so
for the first
two uh levels we had a state of mind
described but then I don't you know you
start to feel like he got lazy and
didn't have a state of mind that he
wanted to talk to us about
um but that's not
true levels 3 to S have the same state
of mind okay so that's just the second
one right the second of the four states
of
mind what is the second of the four
states of
mind
uh from from level three to level
s
um would you think that would you think
the single pointedness is more or the
time off the object is
more the single pointedness is more okay
so State of Mind is single pointedness
but it's interrupted by dullness and
agitation you you have you you are more
on the object than off the object so you
do have you do have pretty much single
pointedness all the way from level three
up to up through level seven okay but
there's a feeling of somebody
interrupting you okay which is uh very
uh irritating right you you enjoy
something you're into something whether
you're eating a meal or you're watching
a TV show or you're reading a book you
know and then someone
keeps uh tapping you on the shoulder and
we talked about it before
that's that interrupts the sustaining
quality of concentration like
concentration is like a food
concentration is like a relief some kind
of mental relief and and pleasure and
then someone is you know ta you on the
shoulder as if you were sleeping and
someone kept waking you up okay then the
ability of the sleep to refresh you is
destroyed right so same with meditation
if there's somebody there who keeps uh
interrupting you or or knocking you on
the shoulder then uh this that's the
feeling of levels 3 to 7 okay you're
trying to concentrate and somebody keeps
interrupting you who uh dullness and
agitation in a group setting like this
there can be two kinds of interruption
and even in a deep Retreat like a threee
retreat uh there can be two kinds of
interruption I mean one is
just uh the person next to you snipple
or the person next to you move or they
crinkle their poster or something like
that okay so you have to be really
careful in a group
setting uh not to do that my my first
teacher was
G and
uh I don't know I met him in uh 1973
okay and
uh then he was teaching us like this in
a great meditation and he took a a
single pencil he had a bunch of pencils
and he took a single pencil and he broke
it and he said that's a person
meditating alone and then he took like
10 pencils and he put them together and
then he tried to break it and he put it
over his knee and he couldn't break it
and he said that's the power of 10
people meditating together you know so
you can feed off of each other's
concentration in a group but you don't
want this tapping on the shoulder thing
which is you know physically it means
shifting or sniffling or by the way
there's as I said before but I don't
know if everybody got it there's no
uh problem with snot just coming down
your face you can open your mouth
breathe through your nose and let this
snot come okay and it just drips and it
it's your
Arizona you know it dries
out uh usually it just needs a little
bit of thing you can you know really now
you don't have to sniff for okay just
let it get see how it see if it works
for you okay just let it go okay and
then you when you get really good at
meditating you you'll do that you'll
just uh when you're hardcore right mix
sure what they
say make
sure you know if when you get to be the
yakuzi of meditation yuzzi right when
you become a heavyweight then you're
just like blowing snot and and you're
just you know the roof concave in and
and you don't stop you know uh somebody
comes in and talks for 10 minutes and
you don't even you don't come out okay I
was meditating in I had I don't know my
last when I came back from GID I rented
a room and I got free rent as long as I
Babys out the kids in the house two two
nights a week it was in a what do you
call Parish house so
uh so anyway I would just meditate and
sometimes the kids would come in I
remember one day the kids came in
they're two like kids they're like 5
years old you know and they came in and
they're like Mike what are you doing you
know and I didn't break my meditation I
just stayed there and then they they
kept yelling like come and play with us
and like you know and I just meditated
and then they they came up and tried to
shake me and I just
didn't and then they sat down and
meditated with me you
know
uh 20 years later I got a phone call
from one of the kids and he saw me on a
on a TV thing in in Manhattan and he
said you know I'm a stock broker in
Manhattan and I meditate and I never
forgot where I'm going to pray I started
the day you were you didn't break your
meditation when we came in you know so
it's cool anyway uh so outside
heavyweight Ching jupa say oh you can't
say Ching jupa means uh continuing
despite
the interruptions by by dullness and
agitation okay carrying through despite
the interruptions by dullness and
agitation is the mental mode from levels
3 to seven
[Music]
uh and that's all that's all on on level
number understand okay it's a little
bit when we get up now into the higher
parts of the chart the whole thing
becomes very theoretical for most of
us
uh so it's a little hard to describe the
differences right so I'd like
to I'd like to more frequently meditate
now okay because because we're I think
now most of you through the beginning of
the cold stage you're sort of into
theing of the C
stage maybe we can push a little
more
okay watch your bre
just your breath one object only only
your breath no other thing in the
world
e e
go to the golden room
feel your teacher hands on your head
and then uh relax into that feeling
stay for a while and what I'd like you
to do is get in touch with your
sh try
to isolate the part of your mind that
catches you thinking about something
else try to meet that state of mind
and and isolate it and and see when it
happens it it catches you thinking about
something
else it could even be a sound in the
room e
find your s find the watch do watch that
State of Mind do its
work it alerts you when you're off
the
e e
now try
to isolate and
observe the heart of your mind which
pulls you back to the
object
t first the alert goes
off and then the Ping back to the mind
they are so quick they are so fast they
are Moments Of Consciousness see if you
can catch a moment of Consciousness see
if you can get to know the inside of
your
mind
e e
okay good job good to come
back open your eyes
I think as you were meditating you might
have become a little curious about
something
like why does a certain distraction pop
up at a certain see I mean
like what's
the what triggers a what triggers an a
the wandering of the mind you see what
why does the mind at 9 at 109 and 30
seconds why does the Mind suddenly
decide to think about something else you
know what's I mean that would
be sort of a different way to go at the
meditation rather
than exerting a certain power or or
pulling out a certain
emotion could
we examine what they call the feel fi of
events right the field of
causation why does stuff pop up at a
certain moment inside my mind you know
why why do I have good days and bad days
in meditation know why is it that some
days the mind is just like
crazy and then why on other days does it
just seem to
flow but but more particularly in a
silent moment of
concentration what what is it that Taps
on my shoulder
who why did he choose to tap at that
moment it seems almost like a a clear
pool of water your mind is like going
well your meditation is going well and
then there's a
blip and what causes the blip you know I
read this book it was like pretty
incoherent
um no very famous author uh what's his
name the judge in British India in 1800s
who became a
yogi uh Arthur
Avalon who was a a very famous
juror and he fell in with some
yogis and then he
he he applied his legal mytic mind he
was a famous
juror and he applied it to yoga the
theories of yoga and he learned to
translate Sanskrit better than almost
anybody and he did it secretly cuz he
didn't want anybody to think he was
crazy but then later he released his
books on Kundalini and stuff like that
but anyway so he has a long section in
one of his books
uh describing the initial impetus of all
things you see because that's a big
problem in in every tradition you see
what what caused the Big Bang that's a
you we're doing quantum physics okay
we're going to discuss what caused the
Big Bang to explain why blip came in
your concentration okay this is quantum
you Ed the infanta small to explain the
large and vice versa right so you know
and and then he has this long then he
goes way off you he gets this long
incoherent thing about why something
should happen at a certain time out of
nothing you know and the whole the whole
conversation is crazy because there is
no good reason why something should
suddenly happen when there was nothing
nothing before if there was truly
nothing before and and of course our
tradition says what there was always
something
before uh but to try to say you know the
the the non Universe was flowing along
fine and then there was a big bang for
some reason and then a universe started
you see what I mean uh without anything
to cause the big bang and then I
somebody ran to me with a uh what do you
call it modern science azine recently
and and they said scientists had decided
there must have been a big bang before
the Big Bang to cause the Big Bang like
a Proto Big Bang because of course you
have to say that there has to be
something to cause it to happen so take
that take that Galactic thing and now
bring it to your little mind trying to
stay in the golden room you know and
there's this little flow of meditation
going and suddenly there's a blip you
know is it just random just did it just
to happen cuz if it's if it is
random uh we're always going to have
blips can you go to the source of the
blips and turn off the
faucet you see can you go to the
invisible source of the blips and turn
off the
faucet
okay and that's uh I hate to say the
word because I sound like Billy Graham
but that's morality okay that's an
ethical way of life okay that's being
nice to others dhra dhra no yoga no
peace
he he would rightly say he would
beautifully say he doesn't say morality
I don't think I've heard him say
morality he just says he says be nice to
other people you know and we' like to
tell this story of uh there's this
famous story that I I heard him in a
class one day he said he was laid for
class on his little bicycle thing his
collaps yeah and he he had cut off a bus
by you know he had swerved in front of a
bus and the bus had to stop and then the
the bus driver yelled at him and then
the bus went on and dar MIT went on and
then Dar MIT decided on his way to our
class that he had offended the driver so
he like pedal really fast and you know
turned down and caught up to the bus and
stopped next to the driver and
apologized you know and that's why he
was late for class right I mean that's
his level of morality okay that's his
level of not hurting other people
okay and then he's the best physically
the best Yogi in the world maybe I don't
know he does a headstand with no hands
just on a on a
sewer you call it a sewer
lud he was in vog magazine or something
I forget the magazine but anyway uh
anyway he's like this upside down and
he's just balancing like on a corner and
uh so
if we can be extremely careful not to
hurt other
people and to encourage and help other
people then we are working at the source
of the
blitz we are shutting off the faucet to
the Blitz in meditation so all this
whole chart is pretty much useless right
uh you are applying antidotes to
Blitz these are after the fact okay the
blip happens and then you work on it
right but but that other approach which
is buried deep in the
text component number five of the six
components of of of preliminaries of
meditation be a nice person don't hurt
other
people if we can go to the source of the
blips and shut them
off uh then then this becomes less
important and that becomes more
important okay so it's good to know how
to deal with blips after they happen
it's good to become a
blip uh m m maintenance
man okay uh but it it would be better to
stop the source of your
blips it's good to learn these things
and it's good to apply the right
antidotes at the right time it's good to
manage your blips blip
manager okay it's good to be a blip
manager uh but I think simultaneously in
a class or a course like this we have to
talk about the source of the blips and
we have to spend some time focusing on
that also you see which means
uh study the yamas and Nas in yogic
terms the yamas and the Yas in Buddhist
terms the 10 virtues okay and what I'd
like to do is put a little attention on
those okay we were in China
we were teaching you know and uh there
Comes A Time In The Diamond Cutter
Institute Retreat where the group
leaders are supposed to explain the 10
virtues to the to their little group
which is typically 10 people so if we
had 300
people that on that day we had 30 people
in the group because we only have 10
teachers we could have we were supposed
to bring 30
teachers
uh but you know everyone's sort of not
looking forward to sitting down with a
group of business people and explaining
the 10 virtues to them uh because
they're afraid they'll they'll think
we're getting religious on them or
something and then the universal
reaction in every country when you and
we also did it at British Airways we
gave a program for the management of Bri
British Air we gave a retreat for the
management of British airs and then you
know we were all kind of not looking
forward to to explaining the 10 virtues
to the Vice President of Operations I'm
pretty sure with you know and then we
did it and there is this intense sense
of relief passed through the room in in
in communist China in British Airways
boardroom you know this intense feeling
of relief like and this acknowledgement
this what do you call
it this instinctive acknowledgement that
this is where we should be and this is
what we should be doing you know and and
this would make the world go right you
know so it was very beautiful whether it
was in London or whether it was in
shanhai uh there was the same sense of
relief kind of poured to the room and
people got into it you know like these
big business people and and these
hardcore you know Communist party
members and they're like they're into it
they got really into it and they were
asking great questions and you could
tell they were passionate about it by
the end of the session you it was really
cool to watch and I observed our
teachers teaching it and it was
fun uh Tina did it in London and like
people like Nimo and mercy were doing it
in Shanghai uh Christine Walsh uh but it
it was cool so my proposal at this
juncture I think tomorrow
sometime
uh what I'd like I talked to Becky about
it what I'd like oh I didn't exactly
talk uh but what I'd like is uh
what we found out on the DCI Retreats is
that it works better in a small group so
what I what I think we'll do but Becky
will work out the logistics but uh the
Wednesday evening
session uh you just stay with your group
in your cabin and a
senior a a diamond mountain graduate
type will come and diamond mountain
graduate means normally they did Seven
Years in New York and they did seven
years so they're good at it uh so they
uh they will go over with you the
10 uh
virtues especially the gray
areas okay which is where where the real
discussion has to take
[Music]
place like respecting other people's
relationships uh do they have to be
married uh what if they are estranged
from each other uh what if they are
divorced but they didn't finish the
paperwork yet you know uh what if
I think I would what if my understanding
was I could date other people but her
understanding wasn't that you know and
like that you know you have to talk
about what constitutes
infidelity
uh so so we'll we'll talk about that so
that'll be Wednesday evening we'll work
out the time in it and then I
thought if you're going to do blip what
do you call it instead of blip
management we're talking about BP
prevention right we're into blip
prevention rather this whole chart is
blip
management maybe we should have spent
more time on blip prevention which is a
lot easier CU then the mind is flowing
and there's not this unexplained blip
you know why did it happen at this
moment why did my mind go off at this
moment
um then Thursday maybe sometime in the
morning sessions we will keep with the
groups in your cabin and go over the
four power
that are used to remove old karmic seeds
Okay old bad karmic seeds so whenever
you talk about the
process of
of of being good to others
simultaneously you have to talk about
how do I clean out all the bad comic
seeds I made before I heard about this
you know and they were many of them
innocent you know in a way I I didn't
you know I didn't know what was the edge
of
of oh this is a committed relationship
or this isn't a committed relationship I
I I didn't think about it when I was 18
and I did so and so you know what I mean
and then uh I still have that seed so so
first you tell
people you know what are the lines and
then you know then they're all upset
because they realize they didn't honor
those lines their whole life and then
they say then the immediate reaction
even in China or even in British Airways
boardroom is uh is there any way to like
you know
it's really cute it's really C doesn't
matter where you are if a if a person's
intelligent which all the people on
Earth are uh then uh then the next
thought is like there you know is there
any like deal you can make about the old
SC and uh so we'll do that Thursday
morning okay we'll figure out some
Logistics like you stay in your C
there's a four-step
process uh outlined by Lord Buddha in a
Sutra called the four
powers uh two 2 and a half thousand
years ago and it hasn't
changed uh the system hasn't changed the
method hasn't changed there's a way to
remove old kic seeds from your mind
so I think to to be good at meditation
to have a good meditation course we have
to address those items those two items
how do you prevent new blits and how do
you deal with the old seeds that you
created that are that are making the
current BL okay and then uh you use that
in conjunction with uh this chart this
is then so you're an expert at blip
management and you become an expert at
blip proactive blip prevention before
the blip
happens there's a thing there's a
beautiful thing I don't know Nima for
some reason it's
called it's aarma
concept I would I would have you repeat
it but you can't anyway ma Mak MAA means
in the future Makwa means won't happen
churen means event okay A non-event a
non-com
event that would be like you know on a
movie they'd say non-com event or
something like this is a movie that's
never going to be finished and you won't
be able to see it
okay I have a feeling some of the
trailers are for movie they never get
finished right on some trailers the
movie never gets finished it's like a
movie that's never going to be finished
they show you the trailer and then they
say you won't be able to see this after
January 10th you know and
uh that's what you want to do with your
blips with the blips in your meditation
you want to make
them you want them to be movies that
never come out the trailer's there
trailer is shown and then the movie
never comes out okay
movie that never comes out that's a good
translation
uh okay then we'll stop there I think
right yeah